Spoiler alert!
Swimming, a popular form
of exercise, easy on the joints,
turns out to not be good
for weight loss.
You're working hard,
burning calories,
so, why don't the inches
and pounds come off?
Watch the video to find out.
"Is Swimming Good for Weight Loss?"
Swimming and aquatic exercise
in general, are popular alternatives
to land-based activities
such as walking or biking.
The buoyancy helps take some
of the weight-bearing stress
off of joints,
but swimming appears to be
less effective for weight loss.
Obese women were randomized
into an hour a day
of walking, cycling, or swimming.
Six months later the walkers
lost an average of 17 pounds,
the cyclists lost
an average of 19 pounds,
and the swimmers
didn’t lose an ounce
(in fact, they actually
gained 5 pounds).
Gauging skin folds
to estimate body fat,
the measurements slimmed
more than 40 percent
in the walking
and cycling groups,
but there was no change at all
in the swimming group.
What’s going on?
And check this out.
The more the women walked,
the more they lost weight.
The more the women biked,
But the more laps they did
didn’t seem to matter.
Even an hour a day.
No weight loss.
What is going on?
Well, it turns out
that some exercise
boosts appetite
more than others.
While land-based exercise
does not stimulate
a compensatory increase
in appetite and calorie intake,
the same cannot be said
for water-based exercise.
In contrast to walking,
in contrast to running,
and in contrast
to cycling,
swimming can significantly
heighten hunger within hours.
This may explain why swimmers
tend to have more body fat
than runners of equal caliber,
even though they may be
actually expending more
calories during training.
If anything, you’d think
swimming might lead
to even greater weight loss since
you’re losing heat to the water.
But swimming didn’t
seem to work at all.
The cold, it turns out,
may actually be the culprit.
If you exercise
in warm water (about 90o F)
it does not boost your appetite
more than exercising on land.
After the same workout
in cool water (about 70° F),
people can end up eating
more than twice as much
at a meal an hour later.
Maybe they’re just burning off
extra calories to stay warm?
No, even at the same number
of calories expended,
people eat hundreds of calories
more after exercising in cold water.
Offered a buffet after burning off
about 500 calories in cool water,
people eat nearly 900 calories,
hundreds more than after exercising
in warm water
or just staying dry.
So, they ended up taking
in about twice as many
calories as they exercised off.
No wonder swimming doesn’t
appear useful for weight loss.
Would the same
thing happen
under different
temperatures on land?
A team of British researchers
sought to find out,
randomizing people
to briskly walk
for 45 minutes on a treadmill
in the cold (about 46° F)
or at closer to room
temperature (about 68° F).
Participants were then
presented with a buffet meal
in which their eating
was covertly recorded.
And calorie intake
was significantly greater
after exercising in the cold.
Though walking is often prescribed
for overweight individuals,
the researchers conclude,
“if walking was to take place
in a cold environment, such as in winter,
then this may stimulate food intake.”
In the warmer months,
though, obesity researchers
suggest exercising outdoors
may be preferable
to an air-conditioned gym.
All studies to date on the effects
of hot and cold environments
have found that exercising
in cool water or under cool conditions
on land led to an increase
in post-workout calorie intake.
What about a quick dip
in the pool after you exercise?
Australian researchers found
that immersion in water
for 15 minutes—cool or warm—
after a running session
resulted in increased
calorie intake.
What is it about getting
wet that whets your appetite?
Maybe they got
a chill after getting out
before they could change
into dry clothes?
This suggests that though
a cool shower after a workout
may be invigorating, it might
be better to stick to hot.